<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Fire + Freedom</title>
        <title type="sub">Freedom + Protest Coverage: Digital Edition</title>
        <author>
          <persName xml:id="JLU">
            <forename>Jessica</forename>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
          </persName>
          <orgName xml:id="AADHum">African American History, Culture, and Digital Humanities (<abbr>AADHum</abbr>) Initiative</orgName>
        </author>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName xml:id="KIYER">
            <forename>Kaanita</forename>
            <surname>Iyer</surname>
          </persName>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>Original text transcribed by</resp>
          <persName ref="#KIYER">
            <forename>Kaanita</forename>
            <surname>Iyer</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>Original TEI template provided by</resp>
          <persName xml:id="RAFF">
            <forename>Raffaele</forename>
            <surname>Viglianti</surname>
          </persName>
          <orgName xml:id="MITH">Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (<abbr>MITH</abbr>)</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      <funder>
          <orgName xml:id="MELLON">Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</orgName>
          <orgName xml:id="FIRE">First-Year Innovation and Research Experience (<abbr>FIRE</abbr>)</orgName>
      </funder>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition n="1">First Edition</edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <extent>
      <measure unit="pages" quantity="9">9 pages of original source material</measure>
    </extent>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>
        <orgName ref="#AADHum">African American History, Culture, and Digital Humanities (<abbr>AADHUM</abbr>) Initiative</orgName>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>
        <settlement>College Park</settlement>
        <region>Maryland (<abbr>MD</abbr>)</region>
      </pubPlace>
      <date when="2018-12-11">11 December 2018</date>
      <availability status="free">
          <p>In the public domain.</p>
      </availability>
    </publicationStmt>
    <seriesStmt>
        <title type="main">Encoding for Black Lives: Legacies of Resistance and Reinvention in the (Re)Making of Black Freedom Online</title>
        <title type="sub">Protest Coverage</title>
        <respStmt>
            <resp>Edited by</resp>
            <persName ref="#JLU">
              <forename>Jessica</forename>
              <surname>Lu</surname>
            </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
            <resp>Texts identified and assembled by</resp>
            <persName ref="#KIYER">
              <forename>Kaanita</forename>
              <surname>Iyer</surname>
            </persName>
        </respStmt>
    </seriesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <title> type="main">Baltimore Erupts After Funeral For Man Who Died in Police Custody</title>
        <title> type="sub">Baltimore erupped in violence on Monday following the funeral for Freddie Gray, a young black<corr>Black</corr> who died mysteriously after injuries sustained while in police custody.</title>
        <author>
          <persName xml:id="JANDER">
            <forename>Joel</forename>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <publisher>
          <orgName xml:id="BF">
            <name>BuzzFeed</name>
          </orgName>
            <placeName>
            <settlement>New York City</settlement>
            <region>New York</region>
            <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
          </placeName>
        </publisher>
        <pubPlace>
          <settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
          <region>Maryland</region>
          <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
        </pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-04-27">27 April 2015</date>
      </bibl>
      <bibl xml:id="JLUDISS">
          <title type="main">Reckoning with Freedom</title>
          <title type="sub">Legacies of Exclusion, Dehumanization, and Black Resistance in the Rhetoric of the Freedmen's Bureau</title>
          <author>
              <persName ref="#JLU">
                <forename>Jessica</forename>
                <surname>Lu</surname>
              </persName>
          </author>
          <publisher>
            <orgName xml:id="UMD">University of Maryland</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <pubPlace>
            <settlement>College Park</settlement>
            <region>Maryland (<abbr>MD</abbr>)</region>
            <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
          </pubPlace>
          <date when="2018-06-28">28 June 2018</date>
      </bibl>
      <bibl>
          <interpGrp resp="#LUDISS" type="freedom-ideas">
              <desc>Ideational analysis of freedom.</desc>
              <interp xml:id="STRAND1">Strand 1</interp>
              <interp xml:id="STRAND2">Strand 2</interp>
              <interp xml:id="STRAND3">Strand 3</interp>
              <interp xml:id="STRAND4">Strand 4</interp>
              <interp xml:id="STRAND5">Strand 5</interp>
          </interpGrp>
      </bibl>
      </listBibl>
      <biblStruct type="article">
        <analytic>
          <author>
            <persName xml:id="SHART">
              <forename>Saidiya</forename>
              <surname>Hartman</surname>
            </persName>
          </author>
          <title>Venus in Two Acts</title>
        </analytic>
        <monogr>
          <title level="j">Small Axe</title>
          <imprint>
            <publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>
              <settlement>Durham</settlement>
              <region>North Carolina (<abbr>NC</abbr>)</region>
              <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
            </pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-06">June 2008</date>
          </imprint>
          <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14">pp. 1-14</biblScope>
        </monogr>
        <note>In this article, Saidiya Hartman theorizes archival violence and its disproportionate impact on the lives of Black women. Hartman argues that archival traces and texts corroborate representations of Black women as always dead or dying, if not in relentless peril. Such violence dehumanizes Black women, not just in the historical record, but also in contemporary life. This theorizing of archival violence contributes to this digital surrogate insofar as every attempt has been made to recognize and amplify the human activities and accomplishments of Black women, with particular attention paid to their life experiences beyond suffering and pain.</note>
      </biblStruct>
    </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
    <editorialDecl>
      <hyphenation eol="none">
        <p>Except where normalization disrupts the formatting of the digital surrogate when rendered online, all end-of-line hyphenation in the original source material has been reformed. The <gi>choice</gi> element has been used to enclose <gi>orig</gi> and <gi>reg</gi> elements giving the original hyphenation and regularized version, respectively.</p>
      </hyphenation>
      <normalization method="markup">
        <p>All obvious spelling and typographical errors in the original source material is corrected. The <gi>choice</gi> element has been used to enclose <gi>sic</gi> and <gi>corr</gi> elements giving the original error and correction, respectively.</p>
      </normalization>
      <normalization method="silent">
        <p>Whenever necessary, spacing between words and following punctuation has been regularized to zero spaces; spacing between words has been regularized to one space.</p>
      </normalization>
      <normalization source="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2017/05/15/the-case-for-black-english">
        <p>Instances of African American Vernacular English have purposefully NOT been adjusted to comply with American English language practices. African American Vernacular English is wholly valid in its form, features, and creativity, despite the dominance and presumed correctness of American English.</p>
      </normalization>
      <p>To represent changes and/or corrections made by the original source authors BEFORE the encoding process, encoders use <gi>add</gi>, <gi>del</gi>, and <gi>subst</gi>.</p>
      <p>Encoding includes the use of <gi>supplied</gi> to provide clarification and supporting content, including out-links to relevant digital content and citations of Black and Black-centric academic research.</p>
    </editorialDecl>
    <projectDesc>
      <p>This project seeks to identify, collect, preserve, and analyze FREEDOM discourse, as constituted and argued by Black users online. Directed by Dr. Jessica H. Lu, this project is currently being advanced by several undergraduate students at the University of Maryland, College Park: Sophia Crooks, Kayla Graham, Kaanita Iyer, Ariana Lawson, Alice Liu, and Courtney Richardson.</p>
    </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="AAVE">African American Vernacular English</language>
        <language ident="us-en">Standard American English</language>
        <language ident="APSTYLE">Associated Press Style
          <note>Since this collection aims to gather journalistic work, many publications use the Associated Press Style to standardize their work. The AP Style focuses not only on grammar but format and synxtax. It is important to recognize this as a language because often times journalistic work can appear more rigid and choppy than spoken word or other writing and that is because of AP Style. For example, it eliminates the word "on" and abbrevaites states, address, and dates, just to name a few</note>
        </language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <listOrg>
          <org>
            <orgName ref="#UMD">
              <name ref="https://lccn.loc.gov/n79054042">University of Maryland, College Park</name>
              <abbr>UMD</abbr>
            </orgName>
            <idno type="LCAF">n 79054042</idno>
            <placeName>
              <settlement>College Park</settlement>
              <region>Maryland (<abbr>MD</abbr>)</region>
              <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
            </placeName>
            <note>The University of Maryland houses the African American History, Culture and Digital Humanities department, which directs and funds this project.</note>
          </org>
          <org>
            <orgName ref="BF">
              <name>BuzzFeed</name>
            </orgName>
              <placeName>
              <settlement>New York City</settlement>
              <region>New York</region>
              <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
            </placeName>
            <note>BuzzFeed is a digital pulication, with a subdivision focusing on news called "BuzzFeed News." Although the company is known for lighter content such as qizzes, memes, and cat videos, BuzzFeed News operates as another other news publication and covers national and internation news.</note>
            </org>
        </listOrg>
        <listPerson>
          <person>
            <persName ref="#JANDER">
                <forename>Joel</forename>
                <surname>Anderson</surname>
              </persName>
            <note>Joel Anderson was the senior national reporter for Buzfeed News at the time of the article's publication. Currently, he works for ESPN.</note>
          </person>
          <person>
            <persName xml:id="FG">
                <forename>Freddie</forename>
                <surname>Gray</surname>
              </persName>
              <note>Freddie Gray's death due to injuries to his spinal cord caused by uncessary force by Baltimore Police while he was in custody, prompted the Baltimore protests and riots.</note>
            </person>
          <person>
            <persName xml:id="MIKE">
              <forename>Michael</forename>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
            </persName>
             <note>Michael Brown was shot by a White police officer in Ferguson, Missouri, prompting similar protests to Baltimore nearly a year earlier.</note>
          </person>
          <person>
            <persName>
              <forename>Larry</forename>
              <surname>Hogan</surname>
            </persName>
            <note>Larry Hogan is the governor of Maryland and declared a state of emergency, while calling the National Guard to manage the protest.</note>
          </person>
        <person>
          <persName>
            <forename>Deron</forename>
            <surname>Martin</surname>
          </persName>
          <note>Deron Martin was a longtime resident of Baltimore at the time of this article's publishing. He commented on the protests.</note>
        </person>
        <person>
        <persName>
          <forename>David</forename>
          <surname>Lemus</surname>
        </persName>
        <note>David Lemus worked at a local, soon-to-be-opened dessert shop at the time this article published. He commented on the protests.</note>
      </person>
        </listPerson>
        <personGrp>
          <persName xml:id="BLK">Black and African American people</persName>
          <note>The identification and amplification of this person group is necessary for the reading and interpretation of this text because the series of tweets describes the journey of a man at a Black Lives Matter protest and how he felt his status as a full human diminish at that moment, even using the historically negative and hateful word "nigger" to describe the feeling.</note>
          <persName xml:id="JOURNOS">Black Journalists</persName>
          <note>As this is a collection of journalist work by Black journalists, it is important to identify this group and recognize that while they are Black people, which makes the protest they cover very personal to them and thus, they are able to make personal connections and often produce better work than journalists of other races covering the same protests, they might always represent the opinion and experiences of all Black people as they do have certain priviliges, including education and a larger voice through their following and support from their publication.</note>
          <persName>Baltimore Police Department</persName>
          <note>The identification, but not the amplification of this group, is necessary for the reading and interpretation of this text because the protest stems from an incident of police brutality and the group was also agrigators at the protest so it is important to acknowledge how their systemic power serves as a disadvantage for Black people wishing to have a voice and express their opinions.</note>
        </personGrp>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change>Capitalized all refrences of 'white' and 'black' when describing race because it is important to amplify Black people in this project as they have been historically disrespected and discredited and I believe it to be a proper adjective, and I also capitalized 'white' when describing race for consistency.</change>
        <change>I created xml ids for the victims mentioned in this article to honor their death and also to signify the impact their death had on the community as it prompted protests.</change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
      <body>
      <p>With sirens wailing from blocks away in all directions, and helicopters whirring overhead, <placeName><settlement>Baltimore</settlement></placeName> spent Monday preparing to burn.</p>
      <p>From his stoop on West North Avenue, <persName>Deron Martin</persName> could see officers and young protesters facing off in the middle of the street about a quarter mile away.</p>
      <p>Behind them were the smoldering remains of the intersection of West North and Pennsylvania avenues, an important intersection in the struggling neighborhood of <placeName><district>West Baltimore</district></placeName>. Only hours earlier, there had been a <orgName>CVS</orgName> store, a <orgName>Subway</orgName> restaurant, a check-cashing business, and a few other small shops near the bus stop there.</p>
      <p>They were all gone now, consumed by flames. And perhaps the anger of neighborhood youth.</p>
      <p>Their anger surged shortly after the funeral of <persName ref="#FG">Freddie Gray</persName>, a 25-year-old <choice><corr>black</corr><sic>Black</sic></choice> man who died on <date>April 19</date> — a week after he somehow suffered a major spinal cord injury while in Baltimore police custody. The violence in <placeName><settlement>Baltimore</settlement></placeName> is a dreadful echo of the unrest in <placeName><settlement>Ferguson</settlement></placeName>, <placeName><region>Missouri</region></placeName>Missouri, that followed the killing of <persName ref="MIKE">Michael Brown</persName>, an unarmed <choice><corr>black</corr><sic>Black</sic></choice> man, at the hands of Darren Wilson, <choice><corr>white</corr><sic>White</sic></choice> police officer who said he acted in self-defense. Since then, the killings of unarmed black<corr>Black</corr> men across the country have sparked a nationwide movement protesting what they see as excessive force by police. On Monday in <placeName><settlement>Baltimore</settlement></placeName>, that frustration with police boiled over into violence.</p>
      <p>"It's from years and years of taking shit," said Martin, a longtime resident and a cook at a nearby soul food restaurant. "Now we're at a point where people just don't give a fuck."</p>
      <p>This hopelessness — expressed by many young protesters in Baltimore — arose from frustration with a system that they believe has consigned them to police brutality, poverty, and even poorer prospects. The streets were filled with children Monday, many of them fresh out of school and itching for a fight with police. By 4 p.m., around the time schools let out for the day, people were hustling out of office buildings, and stores and restaurants were closing their doors to customers.</p>
      <p>Fires burned around Baltimore as law enforcement agencies scrambled to contain the violence. Maryland Gov. <persName>Larry Hogan</persName> declared a state of emergency, activating the National Guard. The Baltimore Orioles canceled their game against the Chicago White Sox. And at least 15 officers were injured as demonstrators threw rocks and bricks.</p>
      <p>"Ain't nobody scared of y'all," shouted one teenage boy, wearing a blue hooded sweatshirt. "This is karma!"</p>
      <p>Much of the damage occurred in the West North corridor's row of small businesses, which mostly includes convenience and liquor stores, hair and beauty shops, and fast food restaurants. Looters also hit nearby <placeName>Mondawmin Mall</placeName>, but officers in riot gear quickly made their way to the scene. Once there, the mostly teenage crowd threw rocks, bricks, and bottles while officers responded with tear gas and pepper spray. In <placeName><district>East Baltimore</district></placeName>, <orgName>the Baltimore Sun</orgName> reported, a senior center under construction was set aflame.</p>
      <p>"Can I get something?" a man said, rushing up to the <orgName>Shake Shack</orgName> in Downtown Baltimore.</p>
      <p>"Sorry," said one of the employees, stacking up chairs on the patio. "There's nothing open down here. It's going to be bad."</p>
      <p>On the Baltimore Police Department's Twitter feed, officials repeatedly warned motorists to stay away from <placeName><district>West Baltimore</district></placeName>.</p>
      <p>In a neighborhood that's been on the decline for decades, Monday's clashes could have been a devastating blow.</p>
      <p>"This has set <placeName><district>West Baltimore</district></placeName> back at least 10 years," said <persName>David Lemus</persName>, who works at <orgName>Frozen Desert Sorbet</orgName>, which had been scheduled to open next week. "I don't know why they choose to do this in the slums and the hood, because this is where those businesses were needed."</p>
      <p>Lemus said Frozen Desert's other store, at <placeName>Lexington Market</placeName> in <placeName><district>Downtown Baltimore</district></placeName>, was damaged in protests on Saturday afternoon. Mostly broken windows, Lemus said.</p>
      <p>But anticipating a repeat Monday, Lemus and a few of his co-workers came out to their store in <placeName><district>West Baltimore</district></placeName> — next door to the Islamic Community School — to protect against any more vandalism.</p>
      <p>They stood by as dozens of children bolted up and down the street, breaking into a pharmacy, clearing off the shelves, and disappearing down side streets. Other teenagers — many of them wearing bandanas to cover their faces from the smoke — came down the street, carrying items stolen from stores farther up the block.</p>
      <p>Lemus shook his head.</p>
      <p>"I know people are frustrated," he said. "But we live here. This is our neighborhood. Tomorrow, when the people want to get a sandwich from Subway while they wait for the bus, it ain't gonna be there."</p>
      <p>He paused. "This ain't about <persName ref="#FG">Freddie Gray</persName>."</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
