<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Fire + Freedom</title>
        <title type="sub">Freedom + Protest Coverage: Digital Edition</title>
        <author>
          <persName xml:id="JLU">
            <forename>Jessica</forename>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
          </persName>
          <orgName xml:id="AADHum">African American History, Culture, and Digital Humanities (<abbr>AADHum</abbr>) Initiative</orgName>
        </author>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName xml:id="KIYER">
            <forename>Kaanita</forename>
            <surname>Iyer</surname>
          </persName>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>Original text transcribed by</resp>
          <persName ref="#KIYER">
            <forename>Kaanita</forename>
            <surname>Iyer</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>Original TEI template provided by</resp>
          <persName xml:id="RAFF">
            <forename>Raffaele</forename>
            <surname>Viglianti</surname>
          </persName>
          <orgName xml:id="MITH">Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (<abbr>MITH</abbr>)</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      <funder>
          <orgName xml:id="MELLON">Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</orgName>
          <orgName xml:id="FIRE">First-Year Innovation and Research Experience (<abbr>FIRE</abbr>)</orgName>
      </funder>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition n="1">First Edition</edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <extent>
      <measure unit="pages" quantity="8">8 pages of original source material</measure>
    </extent>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>
        <orgName ref="#AADHum">African American History, Culture, and Digital Humanities (<abbr>AADHUM</abbr>) Initiative</orgName>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>
        <settlement>College Park</settlement>
        <region>Maryland (<abbr>MD</abbr>)</region>
      </pubPlace>
      <date when="2018-12-11">11 December 2018</date>
      <availability status="free">
          <p>In the public domain.</p>
      </availability>
    </publicationStmt>
    <seriesStmt>
        <title type="main">Encoding for Black Lives: Legacies of Resistance and Reinvention in the (Re)Making of Black Freedom Online</title>
        <title type="sub">Protest Coverage</title>
        <respStmt>
            <resp>Edited by</resp>
            <persName ref="#JLU">
              <forename>Jessica</forename>
              <surname>Lu</surname>
            </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
            <resp>Texts identified and assembled by</resp>
            <persName ref="#KIYER">
              <forename>Kaanita</forename>
              <surname>Iyer</surname>
            </persName>
        </respStmt>
    </seriesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <title> type="main">What It Was Like In The Streets On Ferguson's Worst Night</title>
        <title> type="sub">After promising change, the police let loose with rubber bullets, tear gas, and flash bombs three full hours before curfew. "They didn't give us no warning."</title>
        <author>
          <persName xml:id="JANDER">
            <forename>Joel</forename>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <publisher>
          <orgName xml:id="BF">
            <name>BuzzFeed</name>
          </orgName>
            <placeName>
            <settlement>New York City</settlement>
            <region>New York</region>
            <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
          </placeName>
        </publisher>
        <pubPlace>
          <settlement>Ferguson</settlement>
          <region>Missouri</region>
          <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
        </pubPlace>
        <date when="2014-08-18">18 August 2014</date>
      </bibl>
      <bibl xml:id="JLUDISS">
          <title type="main">Reckoning with Freedom</title>
          <title type="sub">Legacies of Exclusion, Dehumanization, and Black Resistance in the Rhetoric of the Freedmen's Bureau</title>
          <author>
              <persName ref="#JLU">
                <forename>Jessica</forename>
                <surname>Lu</surname>
              </persName>
          </author>
          <publisher>
            <orgName xml:id="UMD">University of Maryland</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <pubPlace>
            <settlement>College Park</settlement>
            <region>Maryland (<abbr>MD</abbr>)</region>
            <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
          </pubPlace>
          <date when="2018-06-28">28 June 2018</date>
      </bibl>
      <bibl>
          <interpGrp resp="#LUDISS" type="freedom-ideas">
              <desc>Ideational analysis of freedom.</desc>
              <interp xml:id="STRAND1">Strand 1</interp>
              <interp xml:id="STRAND2">Strand 2</interp>
              <interp xml:id="STRAND3">Strand 3</interp>
              <interp xml:id="STRAND4">Strand 4</interp>
              <interp xml:id="STRAND5">Strand 5</interp>
          </interpGrp>
      </bibl>
      </listBibl>
      <biblStruct type="article"> <!-- Provided as an example of using the sourceDesc to cite Black scholarship that grounds the encoder's decisions during the markup process. -->
        <analytic>
          <author>
            <persName xml:id="SHART">
              <forename>Saidiya</forename>
              <surname>Hartman</surname>
            </persName>
          </author>
          <title>Venus in Two Acts</title>
        </analytic>
        <monogr>
          <title level="j">Small Axe</title>
          <imprint>
            <publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>
              <settlement>Durham</settlement>
              <region>North Carolina (<abbr>NC</abbr>)</region>
              <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
            </pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-06">June 2008</date>
          </imprint>
          <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14">pp. 1-14</biblScope>
        </monogr>
        <note>In this article, Saidiya Hartman theorizes archival violence and its disproportionate impact on the lives of Black women. Hartman argues that archival traces and texts corroborate representations of Black women as always dead or dying, if not in relentless peril. Such violence dehumanizes Black women, not just in the historical record, but also in contemporary life. This theorizing of archival violence contributes to this digital surrogate insofar as every attempt has been made to recognize and amplify the human activities and accomplishments of Black women, with particular attention paid to their life experiences beyond suffering and pain.</note>
      </biblStruct>
    </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
    <editorialDecl>
      <hyphenation eol="none">
        <p>Except where normalization disrupts the formatting of the digital surrogate when rendered online, all end-of-line hyphenation in the original source material has been reformed. The <gi>choice</gi> element has been used to enclose <gi>orig</gi> and <gi>reg</gi> elements giving the original hyphenation and regularized version, respectively.</p>
      </hyphenation>
      <normalization method="markup">
        <p>All obvious spelling and typographical errors in the original source material is corrected. The <gi>choice</gi> element has been used to enclose <gi>sic</gi> and <gi>corr</gi> elements giving the original error and correction, respectively.</p>
      </normalization>
      <normalization method="silent">
        <p>Whenever necessary, spacing between words and following punctuation has been regularized to zero spaces; spacing between words has been regularized to one space.</p>
      </normalization>
      <normalization source="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2017/05/15/the-case-for-black-english">
        <p>Instances of African American Vernacular English have purposefully NOT been adjusted to comply with American English language practices. African American Vernacular English is wholly valid in its form, features, and creativity, despite the dominance and presumed correctness of American English.</p>
      </normalization>
      <p>To represent changes and/or corrections made by the original source authors BEFORE the encoding process, encoders use <gi>add</gi>, <gi>del</gi>, and <gi>subst</gi>.</p>
      <p>Encoding includes the use of <gi>supplied</gi> to provide clarification and supporting content, including out-links to relevant digital content and citations of Black and Black-centric academic research.</p>
    </editorialDecl>
    <projectDesc>
      <p>This project seeks to identify, collect, preserve, and analyze FREEDOM discourse, as constituted and argued by Black users online. Directed by Dr. Jessica H. Lu, this project is currently being advanced by several undergraduate students at the University of Maryland, College Park: Sophia Crooks, Kayla Graham, Kaanita Iyer, Ariana Lawson, Alice Liu, and Courtney Richardson.</p>
    </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="AAVE">African American Vernacular English</language>
        <language ident="us-en">Standard American English</language>
        <language ident="APSTYLE">Associated Press Style
          <note>Since this collection aims to gather journalistic work, many publications use the Associated Press Style to standardize their work. The AP Style focuses not only on grammar but format and synxtax. It is important to recognize this as a language because often times journalistic work can appear more rigid and choppy than spoken word or other writing and that is because of AP Style. For example, it eliminates the word "on" and abbrevaites states, address, and dates, just to name a few</note>
        </language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <listOrg>
          <org>
            <orgName ref="#UMD">
              <name ref="https://lccn.loc.gov/n79054042">University of Maryland, College Park</name>
              <abbr>UMD</abbr>
            </orgName>
            <idno type="LCAF">n 79054042</idno>
            <placeName>
              <settlement>College Park</settlement>
              <region>Maryland (<abbr>MD</abbr>)</region>
              <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
            </placeName>
            <note>The University of Maryland houses the African American History, Culture and Digital Humanities department, which directs and funds this project.</note>
          </org>
          <org>
            <orgName ref="BF">
              <name>BuzzFeed</name>
            </orgName>
              <placeName>
              <settlement>New York City</settlement>
              <region>New York</region>
              <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
            </placeName>
            <note></note>
            </org>
        </listOrg>
        <listPerson>
          <person>
            <persName ref="#JANDER">
                <forename>Joel</forename>
                <surname>Anderson</surname>
              </persName>
            <note>Joel Anderson was athe senior national reporter for Buzfeed News at the time of the article's publication. Currently, he works for ESPN.</note>
          </person>
          <person>
          <persName xml:id="MIKE">
            <forename>Michael</forename>
            <surname>Brown</surname>
          </persName>
           <note>Michael Brown was shot by a White police officer in Ferguson, Missouri, prompting protests.</note>
         </person>
         <person>
         <persName>
           <forename>Stacy</forename>
           <surname>Graham</surname>
         </persName>
          <note>Stacy Graham was the ally who gave the journalists a ride.</note>
        </person>
        <person>
          <persName>
            <forename>Justin</forename>
            <surname>Jerome</surname>
          </persName>
           <note>Referred to as 'Justin' in this article, Justin Jerome was a friend and former colleage of the journalist at the time his article was published. He is currently the breaking news editor at CBS News.</note>
         </person>
        </listPerson>
        <personGrp>
          <persName xml:id="BLK">Black and African American people</persName>
          <note>The identification and amplification of this person group is necessary for the reading and interpretation of this text because the series of tweets describes the journey of a man at a Black Lives Matter protest and how he felt his status as a full human diminish at that moment, even using the historically negative and hateful word "nigger" to describe the feeling.</note>
          <persName xml:id="JOURNOS">Black Journalists</persName>
          <note>As this is a collection of journalist work by Black journalists, it is important to identify this group and recognize that while they are Black people, which makes the protest they cover very personal to them and thus, they are able to make personal connections and often produce better work than journalists of other races covering the same protests, they might always represent the opinion and experiences of all Black people as they do have certain priviliges, including education and a larger voice through their following and support from their publication.</note>
        </personGrp>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change>Capitalized all refrences of 'white' and 'black' when describing race because it is important to amplify Black people in this project as they have been historically disrespected and discredited and I believe it to be a proper adjective, and I also capitalized 'white' when describing race for consistency.</change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
      <body>
        <p>It was a little after 9 p.m., and I was in the McDonald's parking lot, standing by my car. A police helicopter circled overhead, its spotlight sweeping back and forth.</p>
        <p>Then<add>,</add>I head the sound of shaterring glass: <choice><corr>A</corr><sic>a</sic></choice> rubbed bullet had been fired through a window of McDonald's, which until then, had been one of the few sanctuaries on <placeName><district>West Florissant Avenue</district></placeName>.</p>
        <p>Now I didn't feel safe anywhere </p>
        <p>State troopers in riot gear and armored trucks moved south on <placeName><district>West Florissant</district></placeName>, firing flash grenades and tear gas cansisters at a crowd of protestors who only minutes before had been chanting, "Fuck the police."</p>
        <p>In a panic, I turned to the crowd of officers behind me — some with arms folded, others holding batons — and sought an explanation: <choice><corr>The</corr><sic>the</sic></choice> state-imposed curfew wasn't set to begin for another three hours. Where were we supposed to go?</p>
        <p>The response: "You better get the fuck out of here."</p>
        <p>I'm a reporter, not a revolutionary, so I fumbled around for my car keys, yelled out to my friend and former colleague Justin, and we hopped into my rental car. Leaving through the front entrance wasn't going to work: <choice><corr>The</corr><sic>the</sic></choice> streets were roiling with hundreds of panicked people and the flash bombs were even closer now. So I tried an escape route behind the restaurant hoping I could slip down a back street that would lead us away. But a dumpster prevented our exit. We would have to get out of this on foot.</p>
        <p>In the parking lot, a teenage boy in a white T-shirt and long black sweatpants was writhing around in pain. He screamed that he was on fire. A woman tried pouring water on his face, but it didn't work. A smell like a fevered man's sweat hung in the air — tear gas. </p>
        <p>An older <choice><corr>black</corr><sic>Black</sic></choice> man, probably in his fifties, a hat somehow still perched on his head, protested to no one in particular: "They didn't give us no warning. They just started shooting. There's babies in the street."</p>
        <p>It was true: <choice><corr>Families</corr><sic>families</sic></choice> and older protesters, who usually left around this time on previous nights, were caught in the crossfire. No longer were the police making a distinction between peaceful protesters and the younger, rowdier mobs that took over the street after nightfall. We were all potential anarchists and hooligans.</p>
        <p>Days earlier, Missouri State Highway Patrol Capt. Ronald Johnson, a black <corr>Black</corr> native of Ferguson who had been put in charge of the police response, promised to enforce the curfew without trucks and tear gas. And even though police had broken that promise on Saturday night, Johnson remained popular on these streets. Sunday morning, he had apologized to the family of <persName ref="MIKE">Michael Brown</persName>, the <choice><corr>black</corr><sic>Black</sic></choice> teenager who was fatally shot last week by Ferguson police officer Darren Wilson. It was a moving speech that earned him widespread praise. Even in this community, grown so cynical about the police, Johnson was credibly selling himself as an agent of change. What had happened?</p>
        <p>I fell into the teeming mass of people, most of them <choice><corr>black</corr><sic>Black</sic></choice>, all of them confused. We were being flash-bombed and teargassed back to the south on West Florissant, giving us few options for escape. The most hotly contested sections of the street — in and around the QuikTrip that was burned down during a riot here last week — have no side streets and have been lined with metal gates that penned us in like cattle.</p>
        <p>Most of us continued our retreat on West Florissant, the bombs and gas chasing us to some undetermined location. Some peeled off and ran to their homes in the neighborhoods that line the street. A relative handful — teenagers hopped up on adrenaline and hatred for cops — advanced forward. "We ready!" one yelled, "I'm gonna shoot one of these motherfuckers."</p>
        <p>In the commotion, I was separated from all of my friends and colleagues, and my phone ran out of power (I had gone to McDonald's to recharge it). The streets seemed unusually dark, the lights coming mostly from car headlights. It had been an awfully long time since I felt that vulnerable.</p>
        <p>By now, no one cared that I was a member of the media. I was just a <choice><corr>black</corr><sic>Black</sic></choice> man among hundreds of them. I looked at their faces, scanning for anyone I might know. Some of them had tattoos, or gold teeth, or extravagantly manicured beards. They reminded me of my cousins or friends that I lost touch with. I wondered what police saw when they looked these men in their faces? Did they bother to look them in their faces? I wondered if the police could tell any of us apart.</p>
        <p>Ahead of us (or behind us, as it were) was Chambers Road. At the intersection, I could see the flashing lights of police vehicles — another group of officers were, as Johnson would later say, acting to "protect lives and property."</p>
        <p>Just then, Justin tapped me on the shoulder, and, for a moment, I felt relief. We spotted a middle-aged <choice><corr>white</corr><sic>White</sic></choice> man with glasses and a notepad — a member of the media. I told Justin we should stick close to him. Our proximity to his <choice><corr>whiteness</corr><sic>Whiteness</sic></choice> might get us out of this, safely. I asked him where he worked. He offered a curt response then assiduously avoided us.</p>
        <p>We were almost at Chambers. The officers who were stationed at a nearby convenience store were yelling at us. "Stop running or we will shoot you!" They pointed their guns. I slowed down and raised my arms. "I'm with the media!" I yelled. "What do you want us to do?"</p>
        <p>Justin and I crossed to the far side of the street — to make it harder for them to shoot us if they got an itchy trigger finger. I grew increasingly desperate as I realized that nothing could protect me, not even those sworn to do so.</p>
        <p>Alongside us was a <choice><corr>black</corr><sic>Black</sic></choice> couple, likely in their forties. The man led the woman by the arm and made panicked arrangements for a ride. "Please, Jesus, come get us. Now!" Behind us was a group of boys, none older than 18, who took the opportunity to smash the glass of an auto parts store.</p>
        <p>"Damn!" I yelled at them. "Don't do that shit. They're going to shoot us." The officers kept their guns on us as we walked briskly into the parking lot of a large grocery store. People were hurriedly getting into their cars, skidding their tires to get the hell out of there. I realized then that we didn't have a way to escape. Or even a way to call someone for help — Justin's cell was also out of juice.</p>
        <p>I saw a blonde <choice><corr>white</corr><sic>White</sic></choice> woman getting into a minivan. Something about her — the well-worn sweatsuit? the lack of makeup? — made me think she was a mother. I approached: "Can you please help us?" She didn't even hesitate: "Get on in."</p>
        <p>Her name is <persName>Stacy Graham</persName>. She and her three children — ages 14, 9, and 7 — live 35 miles away in <placeName><settlement>Jerseyville</settlement>, <region><abbr>Ill.</abbr></region></placeName> "So much for the curfew, bitches," she joked when we got into the car.</p>
        <p>Stacy had come to Ferguson to visit her family and show her support for the Brown family. She was wearing a T-shirt that had Brown's face on the front and the slogan "Murder is murder" on the back. Her support comes by blood: <choice><corr>A</corr><sic>a</sic></choice> <choice><corr>black</corr><sic>Black</sic></choice> man, currently serving a nine-year prison sentence, is the father of her three children. "I worry that society has already deemed them doomed because of the color of their skin," she said.</p>
        <p>When we arrived in front of the hotel, I offered Stacy $10 for gas and for all the trouble. "It's not about that," she told me. I insisted and put the money in her ashtray. She got out of her minivan and hugged us long and hard. "If you need anything, call me." We said that to each other.</p>
        <p>About an hour later, Justin and I caught the end of Johnson's press conference on cable news. He offered thanks to his troops for a job well done. Then he read from a script and rarely looked into the cameras.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
