<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Fire + Freedom</title>
        <title type="sub">Freedom + Protest Coverage: Digital Edition</title>
        <author>
          <persName xml:id="JLU">
            <forename>Jessica</forename>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
          </persName>
          <orgName xml:id="AADHum">African American History, Culture, and Digital Humanities (<abbr>AADHum</abbr>) Initiative</orgName>
        </author>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName xml:id="KIYER">
            <forename>Kaanita</forename>
            <surname>Iyer</surname>
          </persName>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>Original text transcribed by</resp>
          <persName ref="#KIYER">
            <forename>Kaanita</forename>
            <surname>Iyer</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>Original TEI template provided by</resp>
          <persName xml:id="RAFF">
            <forename>Raffaele</forename>
            <surname>Viglianti</surname>
          </persName>
          <orgName xml:id="MITH">Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (<abbr>MITH</abbr>)</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      <funder>
          <orgName xml:id="MELLON">Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</orgName>
          <orgName xml:id="FIRE">First-Year Innovation and Research Experience (<abbr>FIRE</abbr>)</orgName>
      </funder>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition n="1">First Edition</edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <extent>
      <measure unit="tweets" quantity="8">8 tweets of original source material</measure>
    </extent>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>
        <orgName ref="#AADHum">African American History, Culture, and Digital Humanities (<abbr>AADHUM</abbr>) Initiative</orgName>
      </publisher>
      <pubPlace>
        <settlement>College Park</settlement>
        <region>Maryland (<abbr>MD</abbr>)</region>
      </pubPlace>
      <date when="2018-12-11">11 December 2018</date>
      <availability status="free">
          <p>In the public domain.</p>
      </availability>
    </publicationStmt>
    <seriesStmt>
        <title type="main">Encoding for Black Lives: Legacies of Resistance and Reinvention in the (Re)Making of Black Freedom Online</title>
        <title type="sub">Protest Coverage</title>
        <respStmt>
            <resp>Edited by</resp>
            <persName ref="#JLU">
              <forename>Jessica</forename>
              <surname>Lu</surname>
            </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
            <resp>Texts identified and assembled by</resp>
            <persName ref="#KIYER">
              <forename>Kaanita</forename>
              <surname>Iyer</surname>
            </persName>
        </respStmt>
    </seriesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <author>
          <persName xml:id="JANDER">
            <forename>Joel</forename>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <name>@byjoelanderson
              <note>Twitter username</note>
            </name>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <publisher>
          <orgName xml:id="TWITTER">Twitter, Inc.</orgName>
        </publisher>
        <pubPlace> Twitter
          <note>Twitter is a "Black place" because it serves as a platform, which is free and accessible to most with a mobile device and internet or cellular data, that allows Black people who have historically been deprived of having a voice to have so and that too with the opportunity to reach a huge number of people within the platform's community of users.</note>
        </pubPlace>
        <date when="2014-08-17">17 August 2014</date>
      </bibl>
      <bibl xml:id="JLUDISS">
          <title type="main">Reckoning with Freedom</title>
          <title type="sub">Legacies of Exclusion, Dehumanization, and Black Resistance in the Rhetoric of the Freedmen's Bureau</title>
          <author>
              <persName ref="#JLU">
                <forename>Jessica</forename>
                <surname>Lu</surname>
              </persName>
          </author>
          <publisher>
            <orgName xml:id="UMD">University of Maryland</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <pubPlace>
            <settlement>College Park</settlement>
            <region>Maryland (<abbr>MD</abbr>)</region>
            <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
          </pubPlace>
          <date when="2018-06-28">28 June 2018</date>
      </bibl>
      <bibl>
          <interpGrp resp="#LUDISS" type="freedom-ideas">
              <desc>Ideational analysis of freedom.</desc>
              <interp xml:id="STRAND1">Strand 1</interp>
              <interp xml:id="STRAND2">Strand 2</interp>
              <interp xml:id="STRAND3">Strand 3</interp>
              <interp xml:id="STRAND4">Strand 4</interp>
              <interp xml:id="STRAND5">Strand 5</interp>
          </interpGrp>
      </bibl>
      </listBibl>
      <biblStruct type="article"> <!-- Provided as an example of using the sourceDesc to cite Black scholarship that grounds the encoder's decisions during the markup process. -->
        <analytic>
          <author>
            <persName xml:id="SHART">
              <forename>Saidiya</forename>
              <surname>Hartman</surname>
            </persName>
          </author>
          <title>Venus in Two Acts</title>
        </analytic>
        <monogr>
          <title level="j">Small Axe</title>
          <imprint>
            <publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>
              <settlement>Durham</settlement>
              <region>North Carolina (<abbr>NC</abbr>)</region>
              <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
            </pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-06">June 2008</date>
          </imprint>
          <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14">pp. 1-14</biblScope>
        </monogr>
        <note>In this article, Saidiya Hartman theorizes archival violence and its disproportionate impact on the lives of Black women. Hartman argues that archival traces and texts corroborate representations of Black women as always dead or dying, if not in relentless peril. Such violence dehumanizes Black women, not just in the historical record, but also in contemporary life. This theorizing of archival violence contributes to this digital surrogate insofar as every attempt has been made to recognize and amplify the human activities and accomplishments of Black women, with particular attention paid to their life experiences beyond suffering and pain.</note>
      </biblStruct>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <editorialDecl>
      <hyphenation eol="none">
        <p>Except where normalization disrupts the formatting of the digital surrogate when rendered online, all end-of-line hyphenation in the original source material has been reformed. The <gi>choice</gi> element has been used to enclose <gi>orig</gi> and <gi>reg</gi> elements giving the original hyphenation and regularized version, respectively.</p>
      </hyphenation>
      <normalization method="markup">
        <p>All obvious spelling and typographical errors in the original source material is corrected. The <gi>choice</gi> element has been used to enclose <gi>sic</gi> and <gi>corr</gi> elements giving the original error and correction, respectively.</p>
      </normalization>
      <normalization method="silent">
        <p>Whenever necessary, spacing between words and following punctuation has been regularized to zero spaces; spacing between words has been regularized to one space.</p>
      </normalization>
      <normalization source="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2017/05/15/the-case-for-black-english">
        <p>Instances of African American Vernacular English have purposefully NOT been adjusted to comply with American English language practices. African American Vernacular English is wholly valid in its form, features, and creativity, despite the dominance and presumed correctness of American English.</p>
      </normalization>
      <p>To represent changes and/or corrections made by the original source authors BEFORE the encoding process, encoders use <gi>add</gi>, <gi>del</gi>, and <gi>subst</gi>.</p>
      <p>Encoding includes the use of <gi>supplied</gi> to provide clarification and supporting content, including out-links to relevant digital content and citations of Black and Black-centric academic research.</p>
    </editorialDecl>
    <projectDesc>
      <p>This project seeks to identify, collect, preserve, and analyze FREEDOM discourse, as constituted and argued by Black users online. Directed by Dr. Jessica H. Lu, this project is currently being advanced by several undergraduate students at the University of Maryland, College Park: Sophia Crooks, Kayla Graham, Kaanita Iyer, Ariana Lawson, Alice Liu, and Courtney Richardson.</p>
    </projectDesc>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="AAVE">African American Vernacular English</language>
      <language ident="us-en">Standard American English</language>
      <language ident="APSTYLE">Associated Press Style
        <note>Since this collection aims to gather journalistic work, many publications use the Associated Press Style to standardize their work. The AP Style focuses not only on grammar but format and synxtax. It is important to recognize this as a language because often times journalistic work can appear more rigid and choppy than spoken word or other writing and that is because of AP Style. For example, it eliminates the word "on" and abbrevaites states, address, and dates, just to name a few</note>
      </language>
    </langUsage>
    <particDesc>
      <listOrg>
        <org>
          <orgName ref="#UMD">
            <name ref="https://lccn.loc.gov/n79054042">University of Maryland, College Park</name>
            <abbr>UMD</abbr>
          </orgName>
          <idno type="LCAF">n 79054042</idno>
          <placeName>
            <settlement>College Park</settlement>
            <region>Maryland (<abbr>MD</abbr>)</region>
            <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
          </placeName>
          <note>The University of Maryland houses the African American History, Culture and Digital Humanities department, which directs and funds this project.</note>
        </org>
        <org>
          <orgName xml:id="BF">
            <name>BuzzFeed</name>
          </orgName>
            <placeName>
            <settlement>New York City</settlement>
            <region>New York</region>
            <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
          </placeName>
        <note>BuzzFeed is a digital pulication, with a subdivision focusing on news called "BuzzFeed News." Although the company is known for lighter content such as qizzes, memes, and cat videos, BuzzFeed News operates as another other news publication and covers national and internation news.</note>
          </org>
      </listOrg>
      <listPerson>
        <person>
          <persName ref="#JANDER">
              <forename>Joel</forename>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
            </persName>
          <note>Joel Anderson was the senior national reporter for Buzfeed News at the time of the tweet and covered the Ferguson protests for the publication. Currently, he works for ESPN.</note>
        </person>
        <person>
        <persName>
          <forename>Stacy</forename>
          <surname>Graham</surname>
        </persName>
         <note>Stacy Graham was the ally who gave the journalists a ride.</note>
       </person>
       <person>
         <persName>
           <forename>Justin</forename>
           <surname>Jerome</surname>
           <name>@JstnMchl
             <note>Twitter username</note>
           </name>
         </persName>
          <note>Justin Jerome was a friend and former colleage of the journalist at the time his article was published. He is currently the breaking news editor at CBS News.</note>
        </person>
      </listPerson>
      <personGrp>
        <persName xml:id="BLK">Black and African American people</persName>
        <note>The identification and amplification of this person group is necessary for the reading and interpretation of this text because the series of tweets describes the journey of a man at a Black Lives Matter protest and how he felt his status as a full human diminish at that moment, even using the historically negative and hateful word "nigger" to describe the feeling.</note>
        <persName xml:id="JOURNOS">Black Journalists</persName>
        <note>As this is a collection of journalist work by Black journalists, it is important to identify this group and recognize that while they are Black people, which makes the protest they cover very personal to them and thus, they are able to make personal connections and often produce better work than journalists of other races covering the same protests, they might always represent the opinion and experiences of all Black people as they do have certain priviliges, including education and a larger voice through their following and support from their publication.</note>
      </personGrp>
    </particDesc>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <listChange>
      <change>Capitalized all refrences of 'white' and 'black' when describing race because it is important to amplify Black people in this project as they have been historically disrespected and discredited and I believe it to be a proper adjective, and I also capitalized 'white' when describing race for consistency.</change>
    </listChange>
  </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="originaltweet">
      <p>Pardon me and my language, but I've never felt more like a nigger than I did <del>" "</del>tonight</p>
      <note>an extra space after "did" and before "tonight" was deleted.</note>
      <div type="newtweet">
      <p>We were lost. A cop pointed a gun at us because we were running, trying to stay away from the tear gas and flash bombs behind us.</p>
      <div type="newtweet">
      <p>It occured to me those officers had no way of knowing I was media. Not that they would have cared. I had to put my hands up and move slowly<add>.</add></p>
      <div type="newtweet">
      <p>The cops continued to yell at us from across the street. I couldn't understand them. I just kept my hands up, &amp; yelled at others to do the same<add>.</add></p>
      <div type="newtweet">
      <p>Everyone was confused. There was literally almost nowhere to go. We went into a parking lot, and cars were peeling off all around us<add>.</add></p>
      <div type="newtweet">
      <p>And I guess my angel is Stacy Graham of Jerseyville, Illinois. I say her backing up and asked her if she would give us a ride.</p>
      <div type="newtweet">
      <p>Dude. A <choice><corr>white</corr><sic>White</sic></choice> woman approached in a dark parking lot by two panicked black <choice><corr>black</corr><sic>Black</sic></choice> men? And she still told us to get on in.</p>
      <div type="newtweet">
      <p>One final thing. As @JstnMchl said: The police are the ones making this dangerous. They risked so many lives tonight...for I don't know why<add>.</add></p>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
